this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
hello this is Philip Winston for
software engineering radio today I'm
here with Adam warsky Adam is a
co-founder and the CTO of software Mill
where he is an expert on Scala and
distributed systems for over 10 years
software mail has used Scala and other
Technologies for custom software
development adamant's also the founder
or key contributor on a number of Open
Source projects including sttp client
sttp to peer enverse quick lens and
elastic mq
Adam has a master's degree in computer
science from the University of Warsaw
today we're going to discuss the scholar
programming language and the tapir
Library let's start just by defining
each of these briefly let's start with
Scala what is Scala and when did you
personally start using it so I started
using what I first encountered Scala
back in my University days on a seminar
on functional programming it seems to be
quite a weird and partly obscure
language back then I was like on the
second year so I was quite young
nevertheless it was quite interesting
but that was like my first first time
when I saw the language then I got into
Java as a paying job and we started to
have a company so about like probably
eight years later
we got our first paying project in Scala
and Scholar was way more popular already
back then
so it was this time it was a conscious
decision to actually try out something
new and um by luck or by choice well
probably half half we ended up using
scholar and you know there's nothing
better to learn a language than actually
writing code in that language and so
thanks to that client and to the
openness of that client to us trying out
a new language we managed to learn quite
a lot and that's how we started can you
give me some examples of problem domains
where Scala is particularly well suited
either that you've worked on or just
from the communities or the precedent
for using Scala well Scala is a general
purpose language right so you can in
theory at least write anything using
Scala that said at least in our company
we mostly use Scala on the back end
so we use it again as a general purpose
backend language so any kind of apis
data processing distributed systems
stuff like that in the communities Carl
is also very popular in the spark
projects through the spark project
however we don't do that much data
science ourselves so that's not why we
use Scala there's also the possibility
of using Scala on the front end through
scholar.js but that's also not a domain
that we've been exploring too much so in
our case it's mostly the back end it's
mostly business code we found Scala to
be very flexible in the way we can
Define abstractions and the way we can
express various domain Concepts
so when using other languages so we've
used Java a lot as well so very often
you were able to express various domain
Concepts in in the language but they
were intermined with some infrastructure
code right so so the domain Concepts
sometimes drowned among all the
infrastructure and all the boilerplate
that we needed to Define as well so with
Scala it's much easier to define the
abstractions which allow you to actually
make a clear boundary between your
business code and your infrastructure
code
so then it's Crystal Clear which one is
which right and this makes it easier to
read the code and to understand it right
if you have the domain Concepts fleshed
out quite clearly
it's quite easy to understand how things
work and then if you have the
infrastructure separate and the
abstractions separately it's also easy
to understand how the whole thing is
orchestrated so I guess yeah that's
that's our main use case for Scala so
talking about back end is some of your
use cases e-commerce or
telecommunications or like what specific
domain we don't really focus on any
particular industry the problems tends
to be very similar as far as backend
development goes right it's the same
problems maybe the words I bet the
difference right so the domains are
different of course and the business
people Express their problems using
different vocabulary
but in the end on the technical side you
end up writing more or less the same
things that's why we don't really we
have a very technical focused company
our specialty is not on an industry but
on the technical side so as I said you
know back-end distributed systems and so
on that said a lot of our clients do
come from some specific Industries so
we've had a couple of clients from Telco
and we had some clients from match Tech
so Medical
we had a couple of clients from the
entertainment industry and of course
fintech is the fourth large group so I
guess you can say that I know maybe they
these are Industries which
have these kind of problems particularly
often
but without any special Focus that's
what we've seen projects being in a
similar industry
let's also briefly talk about Superior
and then we'll dive back for about half
the show into Scala and half into Peter
but I just want to let people know where
we're heading so what problem did you
set out to solve with tapir and if you
can mention the sttp family of libraries
where does tapir fit into that okay so
https stands for Scala HTTP so it's a
family of libraries which are written in
Scala and first color and deal with
various HTTP related problems so as far
as typo is concerned what we wanted to
do is we wanted to expose an HTTP server
alongside with open API documentation so
that was the original problem statement
it's not that easy to do maybe it should
be but it isn't so there are some of
course other approaches one of them is
writing the yaml open API definition by
hand
which I think at programmer students
really have to do because it's not a
language to meant for developers to
write and I think it's more like a
machine language
you can use Java and annotations but
annotations have a lot of drawbacks and
I'm not a particular fan of annotations
so that's another approach and that's
basically it right so these are the two
Alternatives so we hope to find a better
way and that's where top here comes in
so tapir is a library which allows you
to describe HTTP endpoints using ADSL in
Scala using an immutable data structure
and some helper methods to build out the
data structure and to describe the end
point and once you have this description
you can interpret it either as a server
or you can interpret it as open API
documentation
before we go back to Scala for a while
let me mention three shows in past
episodes that are relevant
so on Scala specifically there's episode
171 scholar update with Martin oderski
and episode 62 Martin oderski on Scala
both of those are over 10 years old
though
on functional programming in general we
have episode 418 functional programming
in Enterprise applications
that episode is coming from a.net
F-sharp perspective but it contains a
lot of general information about
functional programming
so let's dive into scholar more focusing
on more recent developments and actual
usage and community
Scala is a jvm language what is a jvm
language and what are some of the
benefits and drawbacks to Scala beam a
VM language so to be precise the jvm is
the main platform to which you can
compile scholar code right there are
also to others so we can also compile
Scala to JavaScript
and to native code as well but the most
popular like from a 90 something
percents of Scala usage comes from the
jvm so can you describe how using the
jvm impacts developer productivity and
also runtime performance I think the
main implication of being on the jvm is
that you have access to the whole jvm
ecosystem
there's probably a library for
everything on the jvm and in the Java so
it might not have a native Scala
interface right so it might not expose
exactly what we would expect from a
scalar Library so it might use different
collections this time might be different
but it's there so in case you really
need it you always have the option to
use the Java libraries for some specific
task
and I think that's a great option to
have
and it makes your life much easier as a
as a programmer so in in some ways you
can think of it as a backup option maybe
if you know if there's nothing in Scala
that fits your needs you can always use
the Java version of of the library or
maybe some even other language however
mixing I don't know a closure library
and then Scala that might be tricky so
probably I wouldn't recommend that
so another thing is that the runtime is
really mature and the garbage collection
algorithm are really fine-tuned so
memory management isn't really a problem
so you can safely create lots of objects
and unless your applications under very
high load you don't really have to care
about that
and you know it's one less problem that
you have to think about as a programmer
so you can just freely create objects
and just dispose of them when you don't
need them and it's a nice property of
garbage collected languages in general
but in Java I think it's one of the best
VMS and garbage collectors out there
which you know just saves you time when
you write your applications so that you
can focus on the business instead of
focusing on for example managing a
memory so of course there are also
downsides of the jvm
startup time being one of them there is
some movement in the Java World project
Laden and just got announced a couple of
months ago which aims to actually
improve the startup time of the jvm but
it's still you know a couple of years
ahead of us right so so for now we have
to live with that so Java as a as a
runtime may not be the ideal choice for
serverless functions or command line
tools
where this extra second daughter really
matters but it's not really an issue you
know for Server applications if it's a
long running process if it starts up in
a second and then continues working for
a month like hookers right and for those
other use cases where you do need this
fast startup time you always have the
option to compile down to native code
using scroll native you can compile down
to JavaScript using JavaScript
or you can use groutvm native image
which I think works particularly well
with Scala in a way probably it works
better with Scala than with Java because
Scala libraries in the whole ecosystem
doesn't rely on reflection
which is a problem with Native image in
Java so I think by coincidence native
image is actually a very good fit for
scholar we're going to move on now from
the jvm but I want to mention one more
episode this is episode 266 Charles
Nutter on the jvm as a language platform
Hollow supports both functional
programming and object-oriented
programming are there communities who
insist on Purely functional code versus
ones that mix the two and where do you
lie on that Spectrum that's a very good
question that's probably the biggest
problem in Scala that there are various
approaches to how you can program using
Scala the language is quite flexible as
I mentioned
and allows you to create a lot of well
very flexible in creating abstractions
which makes people do various sometimes
crazy things and sometimes not crazy but
just original let's say
so there is one part of this color
Community which is a very functional
programming oriented and they do try to
do pure functional programming using
Scala so this usually means working with
some kind of an i o monad and
representing computations as values
this also brings its own problems
because you know to sequence two
computations you need to use flat map
you can't just write two statements one
after another so you need to switch your
whole programming model to a different
approach
and it needs some time to get used to
that model
and it has a certain learning curve of
course once you do get over and do gets
to grog how this pure function and
programming approach works it has its
benefits and it definitely is a very
interesting one
the second approach is a more moderate
and tries to leverage more of the
combination that Scala is between object
oriented and functional programming so
it doesn't reject side effect in
computations in general and doesn't try
to capture every side effect in
computation inside the value
instead in Sky you can use mutable
values you can use you can do side
effects if if you like the language
allows you to do that and the compiler
allows you to do that so the second cam
would be more moderate in that area and
would still use the functional
programming constructs that are there
but not in a very restrictive way right
so I think there are some aspects in
which both communities agree like using
immutable collections it's something
that everybody does
every library in Scala the standard
Library the whole ecosystem is based on
immutable Collections and on immutable
data structures
and that's not something that people
really discuss using right so this is a
very uncontroversial issue
higher kind of types so these are types
which create types that's for example a
more controversial issue with some
people trying to embrace this way of
creating abstractions that Scala allows
and some people try to minimize their
usage to be more friendly for beginners
and there's a couple of more of these of
course
so as for me where I where I stand I'm
not sure yet I'm trying to understand
that it is a dilemma right because on
one hand pure functional programming has
its benefits and it has a certain charm
which is sometimes is hard to resist
because the code can be very elegant and
it has all those nice properties that
the compiler verifies for you
on the other hand I can see that it's
much harder for beginners to understand
it has a higher entry level sometimes
simple things like sequencing some side
effect in computations are not as nice
as they would be in an imperative
language
so you know it's a question there are
always trade-offs in computer science
right so do we want to have this
Elegance of pure functional programming
or do we want to be more practical maybe
and allow some side effects
so it's something I try to answer for
myself to find the golden middle
I haven't found it yet
and it's in fact an ongoing discussion
in the Scala ecosystem especially with
the introduction of project loom in Java
which introduced green threads or
lightweight threats into the platform
which kind of solved in a different way
one of the main use cases for the io
monad for filters in Java which was
asynchronous Computing computations so
now they are like baked into the
language using the direct style of
writing programs so now people started
to wonder like do we use iOS and Futures
and so on
because of their elegance and because of
their functional properties because of
referential transparency because of some
other reasons or have we used them only
for the asynchronous programming aspect
and it is an ongoing discussion and it's
a very interesting one from you know
even from a purely academical
perspective I think
as the libraries which we've mentioned
go so both up here and sdtp they are
designed in a way which works with both
representations so we try to take a
neutral stance
and as I said you know the base data
structures for example the data
structure for describing the end points
it doesn't really matter how you
represent side effects because it's not
concerned with it in fact it tries very
hard to
separate the description of the problem
domain from the business logic and from
the effects that happen
so this allows us to define the
description as a pure immutable value
and it's done the same way whatever
approach in Scala you prefer and then
you can Define the business logic so
whatever happens when you invoke the
endpoint with whatever representation of
side effects you prefer and you choose
so in this respect we try to work with
everybody of course it's not with its
own like it has some downsides so the
the API is a bit more complicated
because of that but it is possible to
actually use the same Library whatever
Scala style you are using you mentioned
monads once or twice I'm gonna refer to
episode 266 to Define that
so can you give an example of a purely
functional library or framework that you
really like in Scala besides your own
and then maybe one that
is more object oriented or has side
effects that you
feel is popular and you like despite
those limitations or those choices so
just to again be precise tapir isn't
really all pure functional programming
because it works with both sides right
so
it is functional in its style but it
allows you to work with both Styles as
far as functional libraries go
I think that two particular nice
implementations of libraries which
Implement support for purely functional
side effects one is called Cuts effect
and the second is called Zio they both
try to solve the same problem in a bit
different way and it's also interesting
to see how they in a way compete and how
they implement the same features so when
one Library implements a feature the
other tries to catch up and vice versa
but they also sometimes make different
decisions so it's very educational to
actually see the development going on so
the problem domain that trying to solve
is representing computations which might
involve side effects as a value
once you have a computation represented
as a value you can do a lot of things
with it in particular you can pass it to
functions which somehow modify this
computation right so for example you
have a computation which represents
fetching something from a web page right
and now you can pass it to a timeout
method which will modify this
description of a computation
to return another description of a
computation which will actually impose a
Timeout on the whole process and so on
there's a lot and there's a lot of these
combinators which allow you to modify
how these descriptions where they allow
you to build larger descriptions from
smaller descriptions and more complex
one from simpler ones
and as far as any kind of concurrency or
false tolerance goes there's probably an
operator for that in both of these
libraries
they differ in in some details in how
they handle concurrency but the biggest
difference I think is the way in which
they handle errors so in Zio we have a
dedicated error channel so each
computation is defined through its type
not only by the type of value that the
computation produces once it is run but
also by the type of the error which
might happen when the computation is run
so this way you can Define computations
which should never fail and should never
return an error by just saying that the
error type is nothing which is a type
which has no inhabitants or you can say
that arbitrary exceptions may occur for
example so this is an interesting
approach to how errors can be handled
and this is done very nicely throughout
the Zio library and other Zio libraries
as well and very consistently
so so you know error handling is in
general a very important subject as
errors actually Define how you write
your code right and it's the number one
concern you should have when writing
code what will happen when things go
wrong
so these are the function libraries
which I think are very interesting to
take a look at as for not purely
function libraries I think I would say
akka is the most interesting one
unfortunately it has been moved from an
open source license to a source
available license in the recent days
but nevertheless the library is
interesting in itself as well so
archives and implementation well
archives is a lot of things but at its
core it's an implementation of the actor
model for the jvm it's available both in
Scala and in Java but the implementation
itself is in scalar so the actor model
is one where you have actors which can
enclose some Behavior and the only way
to communicate with those arcsources by
sending them messages in an asynchronous
way and it's not purely functional
because actually sending a message to an
actor is a side effecting operation
right so it's like a fire and forget
so that's not purely functional at all
quite the opposite however the way you
can Define actual Behavior can be done
in a functional way and akka has a very
nice API for that apart from that akka
has great apis for streaming and for
http
which I think are one of the most
programmer friendly ones I would
probably use akhtp to write an HTTP
server if I didn't used up here but yeah
but for example as far as streaming goes
it's also the most developer friendly
API out there there are other apis for
defining streaming computations in skull
as well and they are great but I think
akka streams still has an edge over them
in terms of how easy it is to understand
the code and to write the code
and one thing to say about akka although
it is now becoming not full of Open
Source there is an initiative to create
a fork in Apache so maybe the open
source AKA will continue in some form
you mentioned three libraries I'm going
to look those up and put them in the
show notes I'll put links to them
Scala is strongly typed can you talk a
little bit about how scala's type system
compares to Java one of the trends we
see in the industry is python adding
gradual typing through typins and
typescript adding sort of gradual typing
to JavaScript what benefits do you see
from Scala having strong typing from the
beginning and if you could just give one
example into peer or another Library
where something sophisticated was done
with the types that really helped the
implementation
so I think first of all the static
versus Dynamic typing is a matter of
taste in many cases and personal
preference
so I doubt there ever will be a clear
winner as to you know which approach is
better I think both are good just some
people prefer to use one tools and other
people prefer to use other tools right
so in my case I've always liked static
typing I have always liked the fact that
the compiler checks all those boring
properties for me
and these are the properties which are
proved to be correct and I don't have to
write tests for them right
and I think the fact that both python
introduced some form of static typing
that typescript exists and so on this
kind of validates the fact that in large
code bases
and in more complex systems you do need
the static types to navigate code
especially in cases where you can't fit
the whole system in your head
and when you work on somebody else's
code when you got introduced to a
project that's when even the simplest
types are very beneficial just for code
navigation
you know and for naming things this
might be trivial well they might seem
trivial properties but they're actually
very helpful I think
so as for Scala and Java and their type
systems so this Scala type system is
actually very irregular
and in some ways it might also be viewed
as simpler than Javas well it's kind of
in general as a language is actually a
lot simpler than Java because it has way
less special cases and Corner cases and
probably the same goes for the type
system so so as far as the language goes
the grammar size might be an indicator
and that's a property that Martin
odersky the creator of scholar often
shares that the grammar size for Scala
is actually much smaller than the
grammar size for c-sharp Java and so on
the language is just way more regular it
has a couple of features that you can
always use and it's the intersection
between the features that give the
language its power anyway going back to
the type systems so everything you can
express in Java you can express in Scala
as well and however Scala has a number
of additions which again make it more
regular but also make it more powerful
so higher kind of types which I have
already mentioned are one example so in
Java you've got you've got the generics
so you can parameterize your class with
some type in scale you can do the same
but it can also parameterize a type with
a type Factory so you can parameterize a
class with for example some kind of a
Constructor which needs to be provided
with a type to produce another type so
an example of a tab Constructor is a
list right a list in itself is not a
type it's a tab Constructor you need to
provide it with the type of the elements
to actually get a type so a list of a
string is a proper type and the list is
type Constructor so you can use those
higher kind of types to create
abstractions and that's very useful and
appear in the way we Implement our
integration with various approaches to
handing side effects in Scala so when
you provide the business logic of an
endpoint which I've also mentioned
earlier you need to provide a function
which takes the input parameters and
produces the output parameters which are
then mapped to the HTTP response and
this function needs to produce the
output parameters using some kind of
effect right it can be the i o effect
from Cuts effect it can be the desire
effect from Zio it can be featured from
acap it can also be the identity effect
if you would like to use project loan
for example and you know write
synchronous direct style code that's
also possible but because this server
logic function is parameterized with a
higher kind of type you can just plug in
everything there so that's the kind of
flexibility that Scala allows and it's
just a no-brainer to actually do that
Scala also has especially a useful I
think other types that come with color 3
there are some new kinds of types that
got introduced which are not so well
known yet I guess in the wider audience
so for example new types known and Scala
is opaque types these allow you to
create a zero kind of a zero cost
abstraction so they allow you to wrap an
existing type with something that is
distinct from that type at the
compilation time
so for example you can wrap a string
into an email type
and when you compile things this email
type will be different from a string so
you can't mix those two right but at
runtime everything is erased and this
opaque type behaves just as a string
without any runtime or any runtime
overhead
and there's a couple of my examples of
these types that have been added to
Scala as for when how tapir uses it so
I've already given one example how you
can Define the business logic but I
think going one step earlier
is the way it appear provides type
safety of its input and output
parameters so
when you
describe an endpoint using tapir you do
so incrementally you incrementally
define the inputs of an endpoint
and the outputs so the inputs are the
things that are extracted from the HTTP
request so this might be a query
parameter this might be a header this
might be the request body for example
and you incrementally say that you know
this endpoint has a query parameter and
name that should be read as a string it
has a header something which should be
parsed as an INT and it has a Json body
right so you just call three times a
method which adds an input
and the type of the end point each time
is extended by the type of the input
that you add right so if you add three
inputs a string an INT and a Json body
you end up with a tuple which has three
elements corresponding to these types
and the same thing is done with the
outputs so then when you need to define
the logic of the endpoint you need to
provide a function which has this exact
type right so everything is well typed
and verified by the compiler and I think
that's nothing particularly fancy in
Scala to actually build those tuples it
is like some very simple type level
programming which you can do but it has
very nice compile time properties so
that you can see the shape of the
endpoint what are the inputs and the
exact type and the outputs
a very important property here is that
once you write an endpoint the IDE can
infer the type of the endpoint right so
you don't have to write it by hand you
can just click in IntelliJ or whatever
ID you use to please infer the type and
you will get the correct type generated
for you
so we got into appear there relative to
the type system but I wanted to call out
one thing you mentioned which was
scholar three so Scala 3 was released in
2021 after maybe eight years of
development
I just wanted your opinion on how the
transition is going from two to three
python famously had a very long
transition period I think more than 10
years in some sense can you just talk
about how that transition is going for
either your work at software Mill or The
Wider ecosystem and maybe mentioned an
additional besides the type changes an
additional scholar 3 feature that you
like and maybe one that you're less
excited about or or that maybe your have
reservations about
sure so I think that everybody hoped the
migration will actually go faster
but as always things go slower and
that's nothing that's exceptional in
skull I guess just I don't know rule of
life
Scala is as a you know as an
introduction to that subject Scala is
much better suited for such migrations
than python because it is statically
typed
and you have the compilation phase and
the compiler will actually tell you if
things work or not up front right so
that's one thing but another thing is
that because of the types there is a
chance to write a tool that migrates
Scarlet two codes to scar 3 code and
such tools do exist there are some
syntax changes there are some semantical
changes and there are some tools which
will actually allow you to migrate the
code base
so that's not a big problem the bigger
problem is the ecosystem and how fast
all of the libraries get migrated so
there are some libraries that have
migrated very fast there are some
libraries that are catching up right now
there are some which are like still
lagging behind akka here being a prime
example there still is no release of
akka for Scala 3 unfortunately so it
depends which part of the ecosystem you
are using in our company we are still
mainly using Scala 2 we are only
starting our first class 3 projects I
think either this or next month
so it's slowly getting there but some
work still needs to be done especially
in the ecosystem migration because you
know that simply requires manual labor
and it requires often to maintain two
versions of the code base right so there
are some not very common but in some
cases you do need to have different code
for scalato and for scholar 3. so you
can share most of the code but you also
need to actually create two different
parts of the source that one is included
in this character and one is in
conditions class three and you know
being a maintainer of of HTTP I can say
that maybe it's not a big problem but it
does take some time to actually do
however I haven't seen like any big
problems out there it's it's not like
there are some showstoppers or there are
some major obstacles apart from people
having to invest their time which is
understandable you know it's open source
you can't really expect people to do the
work unless you know you in a business
relation with them
so you can either do it yourself or you
can wait for others when they have time
so I'm optimistic as to how this will
progress in the future I think in a year
or so we will see a much higher scholar
3 adoption and there are also companies
including mine which invest in Scala and
in Scala touring and in the migration
efforts of Scala so hopefully this will
pay off
as for this color 3 features I think my
favorite feature and I think something
that is unique to Scala in general is
its macro system so macros have been
present in scalato as an experimental
feature they have seen two or three
iterations of how the macro is being
written and defined however in Sky 3 we
get a brand new way of actually writing
macros which is a good thing because the
new way of writing macros is much more
principled and it's cleaned up and is
much more friendly for developers in
certain aspects
however it also means that if you have
used a macro since carto you now have to
rewrite the macro in a completely
different way into scholar 3 and that's
like one big part that is not compatible
between those two releases I think it's
the only major part in fact
however macros actually allow you to do
a lot of things so macros allow you to
generate code at compile time using
Scala code so you write Scala code which
manipulates the abstract syntax tree of
your program and generates some other
code at compile time so that it's
compiled later by the Scala compiler and
I think it's a great replacement for the
annotations that are used or abused in
Java very often so in Java for example
if you want to encode or decode Json you
will often see classes annotated with
Json mapping annotations and then at
runtime these annotations are read using
reflection and some bytecode is
generated to actually handle the
serialization industrialization and you
know it works it has its downsides I
think there's quite a lot of downsides
using annotations in Java this way into
relying so much on reflection and I
think there is a better way through
micros here what you can do instead said
is you can sometimes even also using
annotations but these annotations are
processed at compile time so you can
generate code which will actually handle
the Json reading and writing and one big
benefit here is that any errors that
might happen in so any no mistakes in
the mapping will actually get caught and
and surface at compile time instead of
runtime also the runtime penalty is
lower because you can just generate code
once when you compile instead of doing
it over and over again at runtime when
the application starts up and also the
API for actually generating the code
well it's it's just color code that you
write it's not some annotation processor
or it's not some reflection API that you
have to rely on it is simply is color
code that generates others color code
but macros is maybe I shouldn't even say
that I shouldn't call this feature
macros it's a whole meta programming
aspect so macros are just one part there
are also inline functions which
sometimes even allow you to do a lot in
terms of code generation without
actually writing a macro so you just can
write some inlines you can do
conditionals in that you can do pattern
matching in there on types all at
compile time so that's a feature I
really like and I think it's quite
unique because in Java you cannot do
anything like that or in kotlin so I
think that's something that really
stands out as far as languages on the
jvm in general go as for the feature I
wouldn't like so much in scar 3 that's a
good question I don't really know I
don't know
that's fine it was interesting to hear
about Scala 3. now I want to shift gears
to peer itself obviously if you want to
reference a Scala feature relative to
tapir that's great but to appear version
1.0 was released this summer June 2022
to Bear started development I think in
what was the path like from origin to
release of 1.0 and can you give just one
specific example of maybe a technical
issue that was difficult to overcome or
took a lot of effort and then maybe a
community issue as far as attracting
attention to the library so I must say
that tapir caught on pretty quickly so I
think it it solved a really common
problem that people had that people
really wanted to generate documentation
out of their endpoints and the other
approaches that I mentioned aren't
really that great and it appear here
really felt a niche that needed to be
filled there were also other approaches
like endpoints for S which I think still
do exist they take a bit of a different
approach but in general they try to
solve the same problem of how do you
define an endpoint alongside with the
docs that said as you said the
development of tapir took about four
years of the appear one zero it's not
like finished finished it's just the
core module out that's declared as
stable I'm not sure if it was a
community issue I think it was just a
good community that we managed together
but it appears a lot of iterations on
various design elements
so quite often we had like I think 20
minor releases so
0.10.2 up to 0.21 or something like that
and each of them actually meant that you
had to rewrite part of your code which
probably isn't such a great experience
for you know people using tapir but they
did they did migrate from version to
version and they did report problems
back so that was very helpful in
actually understanding how people use
the library what they expect and so on
still you know it was a zero dot version
so some breakage is expected I guess but
I think we have they were very patient
into how we try to find the best
representation for various Concepts
can you give some examples of production
applications that are built with tapir
maybe not just companies but actual
applications people might have heard of
or that you just feel are a good
representation of what to pair can do we
use tapir a lot inside our company
because we built applications for our
clients I can't share their names
unfortunately out of obvious reasons
it's not usually that you know the well
it appear functionality in a way is
user-facing because you end up using a
rest API you wouldn't know that it's up
here right it can be any other Library
out there the same if you take a look at
Swagger the editor or the open API docs
you wouldn't know that it's generated by
tapir right just standard format so
there's a list of tap your adopters on
the tapier documentation site and
there's a couple of companies that
publicly agreed to share their names
so if you're interested you can take a
look over there beside that I don't
really know you know how wide is that
previous it's very it's in general a
hard problem in open source right
getting to know is your library used or
not there are some indicators like how
often do you get bug reports so if you
do get back reports then obviously
people do use your library
and in tapir I guess we get a fair
amount of questions sometimes bugs
sometimes future requests so which shows
a certain kind of activity which is very
encouraging and very promising you can
also take a look at the number of
downloads in the maven Central however
that's you know very inaccurate right
because it's just CI systems downloading
the same stuff over and over again
although it does give you some
indication so again here I don't
remember I have no idea what are the
exact numbers or anything like that but
we can see some nice growth into how
tapir is being used so it's either
people just running their builds more
and more often or it's actually a new
projects being created with appear
but you know and I think as I mentioned
in the beginning because we are talking
about exposing a rest API it's not any
particular type of problem domain right
most projects nowadays need an address
API of some sort and you need to
document the API for others to consume
it so the nice thing about tapir is that
you describe your endpoints once and you
do that using a high level language and
the type safe language
instead of writing yaml when you write
an endpoint using tapir you not only get
type safety you also get code completion
you get the compiler verifying that the
types at least at the basic level match
so these are some important
characteristics when it's when it comes
to the developer experience of actually
writing well the task of exposing a rest
API probably isn't the most interesting
one right you can think of more exciting
things
so I think it's important that we
actually have a good and efficient way
of describing how the API should look
like and one thing I think that's also
worth mentioning is that you can also
interpret a tapir endpoint as a client
so you can use the same description to
actually call an endpoint that you have
exposed so if your clients are also
written in Scala it might be scarlet.js
and it might run in the front end oh it
might be another microservice you can
also use the tape description to create
a client and call out your service which
is being described by tapir you can even
go as far as describing other services
using the tap your data structures and
maybe documenting them even if they are
not even if the server doesn't run using
tapir and you know generating docs
basing on that I think some people are
doing that and I can't blame them I
would prefer describing endpoints using
a high level language and they're
properly typed language instead of yaml
which I'm not a particular fan of
what do you feel is the primary
difference between a library and a
framework I'm assuming that tapir is a
library do you feel that Scala as a
language biases people more towards
libraries or is it also possible to
write a framework in Scala and do you
maybe have an example of a framework
that you do actually use in Scala and
just kind of contrast the two right so I
think the difference might be subtle but
the major difference is how you actually
use a certain piece of code right with
the library you are in full control and
you decide when to invoke the
functionality in that dependency right
so it's you invoking the library not the
library invoking you of course you can
get callbacks and so on that's normal
but it's about the main mode of
operation how you actually structure and
write your code whereas in a framework
you have to adapt to the way the
framework imagines your structure and
write your code and you have to follow
the recipes that the framework authors
have created for you so in a way it's
much more constraining which can be a
good thing and a bad thing a good thing
because it's actually you don't have to
think about how do I structure my code
because it's already there right it's
already defined by the framework author
it's a bad thing because it constrains
you well so it's a double-edged sword
not right sometimes constraints are nice
and in a way liberating as rooner said
in one of his talks so tapio definitely
falls in the library category
so there is nothing prescriptive in
tapir as to how you should write your
code
you use the tapier apis to describe the
endpoint you use the copyright apis to
couple the endpoint with the server
logic that should be run when the input
is invoked but then you know where you
define the endpoint how you actually
where the logic lives right you just
need to pass in a function so where that
function is defined is it defined in
some other class that is I don't know
wired using some dependence injection
library or maybe you are just using
Singleton objects whatever it's not a
concern of tap here and you just need to
pass in the functions and then you pass
in this description into another
function which turns it into a server
which you still have to start right so
in all stages it's your responsibility
to actually invoke the tap your
functionality and you have to include
all of that in your code base which I
think is a good thing because it allows
you to actually have an application with
the main method wherein the main method
is like the main entry point not only
into the application but also to reading
the application reading the code so you
can
again using a simple called navigation
in the IDE you can understand what
happens step by step when the
application starts and where the
components are defined so there is no
you know magic auto Discovery whatever
so I think this Library approach is
actually at least for me much easier to
follow and to understand as I have
clearly clear places in code where I
know things happen right and I I know
that other things won't happen unless
they are written in the main function
and code reachable from that main
function and I think that's an overall
approach in Scala Scala as an ecosystem
and as a community either the functional
one or the less functional one they both
tend to prefer libraries over Frameworks
I think maybe in a way Zio tends to go a
little bit in the direction of a
framework than a library but it's also
quite subtle and you can still use IO as
a library as well akka here is also an
example at least in some parts of its
functionality where it is a bit
framework like but you can still use
akka as a library if you prefer to do so
all of its components are usable
Standalone so you will well you will
always get the dependence on a cacao for
example but you can use the streaming
independent of HTTP and so on so I don't
think there will be like a Scala
framework coming
maybe instead what will happen is we
will see some kind of an integrated set
of libraries being introduced so
libraries which are documented in a
similar way which behave in a similar
way maybe which you know are configured
in a similar way so just that you can
have the same feeling when using the
library you know what to expect what
kind of approach to expect because the
code style is similar the naming
conventions are similar and so on so I
think we might see something like that
and I would would definitely be a fan of
this idea because as I said I do prefer
libraries over Frameworks I think they
give you the right amount of control but
of course you don't want to learn a new
approach with every Library so having
some integrate set would actually be
very nice to have in the sky ecosystem
and this might be happening there's an
initiative led by skeleton and virtus
lab which is called Scala toolkit and it
will contain a number of libraries which
are like a companion to the standard
Library
so there will be for example a library
to parse Json there will be a library to
access the file system and the part of
it also will be a CTP client which will
allow you to make HTTP client requests
and the goal here is to create a toolkit
for which you have the documentation in
one place in a similar format and the
Integrations are there so that one part
of the toolkit was with another and so
on so that's I think coming sometimes
next year I'll definitely put links to
that project in the show notes
two kind of technical topics into peer
documentation that sounded
I don't know if they're unique but not
commonly used phrases one was server
interpreters and one was interceptors I
thought it'd be interesting to hear your
explanation of of what these two are
what value do they provide and and maybe
if you know are they general concepts
used outside of tapir and just kind of
let us know about that sure first let's
maybe talk about the interpreters the
first thing that you do with tapir is
you describe an endpoint using our API
right you get an immutable value which
is a scription but it's it's just that
right it doesn't contain any logic as to
what should happen when the endpoint is
invoked it doesn't contain any logic as
to how to expose a server to the outside
world it's just a data structure with
the metadata right it also allows us to
cleanly separate the structure of the
endpoint the shape from actually any
code that implements the business logic
so this is the first step now you would
probably want to actually expose a
server right and for that tappier has
server interpreters so tappier itself
doesn't Implement an HTTP server there's
a ton of great HTTP servers out there
and writing yet another one probably
would be a long effort and I'm not sure
if you would Implement anything better
than already exists so instead you can
take an endpoint description
put it inside the server interpreter
which is just a function in the end and
it turns the description
into some kind of other representation
that is understood by an actual HTTP
server implementation so for example
there is a Neti interpreter Neti is a
networking library for for Java but it's
also usable in Scala so you can take a
tap your endpoint
put it inside the Neti server
interpreter and you get an Neti Handler
which you can attach to a Neti server
and expose it on the web in a similar
way you have an archived interpreter
which converts an endpoint into an AG
car route which you can then expose we
also have interpreters for vertex for
play for armeria for HTTP 4S and
probably some others as well the latest
interpreter is for a helidon Nema which
is the loom first implementation of an
HTTP server in Java using project loan
so these interpreters are you can think
of a of them as functions which take the
description of an endpoint and turn it
into an actual server which you can then
attach to a to some server
implementation and and we provide nice
apis which allow you to actually expose
those endpoints so that you don't have
to write too much code so that's one
part the interceptors on the other hand
they're also part of the server aspect
of tapir so there are some cross-cutting
concerns which you want to address for
example for example exception handling
for example Gathering metrics or what
should happen when a parameter can't be
decoded because I know the Json body is
malformed or you are expecting it in and
the query parameter that you said you
wanted to be is that it should be an
integer but it's actually you know a
string and it doesn't pass so these are
some components which you can plug in to
the server interpreter and you can
specify that behavior for all endpoints
usually you don't want to specify this
in a different way for each endpoint
right the if an exception happens inside
your server logic each for whatever the
endpoint is you probably want to just
return a 500 internal server error log
the exception and go further right a
nice thing about interceptors and the
way tapier endpoints are defined is the
way we can handle observability so one
of the interceptors that's there by
default is the Matrix Interceptor which
well you have you have to enable it but
it's part of the tapiro project
so we can actually leverage the
structure of the endpoint as it is
described in the data structure to
provide some more information for
metrics for logging compared to what we
would have if the endpoint was just an
opaque entity right so for example the
Interceptor knows and it gets a call
back that the request is matching a
certain endpoint and that we will
actually try to invoke the server Logic
for that endpoint right because the
query parameters match the path matches
the headers much and so on so using that
knowledge we can actually log some more
information that you know now we are
trying to invoke an endpoint with a
given name or with a given path with a
given past template right because maybe
the past included some variable elements
some variable path segments and this
makes it much easier to implement both
metrics and end logging in a nice in a
nice way because you have access to that
whole endpoint metadata that is defined
with the endpoint description
so I think we're talking somewhat about
what's called observability I think
today maybe that includes error handling
logging any debugging features rather
than get too deep into
those let's maybe hear a real world
debugging story a time that you had to
use some of these observability features
to you know you can change the names a
little bit but to debug a specific
problem right so debugging it's not
always that easy in Scala so that's
actually one of the weaker sites I would
say in Scala especially when you use the
effect systems that is because they
Multiplex your code onto multiple
threads right and this way they allow
you to write code which uses a library
level fibers or green threads on a
bounded thread so this might change with
project Loom but so far we are on the
old Java implementation
and because of that the stack traces
aren't always that informative because
you can get a very short stack Trace
just you know with the internal run Loop
exposed in the stack Trace instead of
the whole history of where you the
invocation actually came from so this
makes debugging not as easy as is my as
it might be and sometimes you just need
to rely on the backlogs or print lines
which is I think the most popular the
banking method out there so yeah so but
that's like Scala in general as far as
tappier goes a very nice feature is that
we can actually see and we can enable it
in tap here which endpoints is attempted
to be decoded one by one so by default
that's not turned on but if you have
some problematic endpoints and
especially in the early days of tapiro I
often got bug reports that people were
expecting that a certain endpoint is
invoked but it didn't or that at the end
points are invoked out of order or
something like that so what you can do
then is you can enable this detailed
logging which allows you to see that
well The Interpreter tried to decode the
request for this particular endpoint but
the query parameter called age didn't
match so we rejected this right and we
go to the next one and here the path
didn't match so we go to the next one
and here we try to decode the body and
once we try to knock out the body we
don't write any subsequent endpoints
because we've already consumed the HTTP
request so we just return and 400 bad
requests right so you can see this
detailed trace of what the server is
actually trying to do and in cases where
you actually expected an endpoint to be
invoked but it didn't that's very
helpful and that's what I often use to
debug various problems that people
report when using tapir let's start
wrapping up can you tell me what's next
for tapir either as far as features
Community adoption what do you see
taking up your time in the next year or
so
right so as I said I think we are going
to explore the direction in which Scala
and the Scala libraries would evolve and
well both try to observe the community
and maybe take a take part in the
development itself as well so there's
the question of how effects should be
represented in Scala should we focus on
the functional representation of effects
so the io monad should we go the loom
way so using direct style code there's
also a research project that aims to add
capabilities to scalawatus I think it's
going to be an implementation of
algebraic effects so something that
allows you to capture what kind of side
effects a certain function performs
inside the type signature but without
using monets so it's trying to do the
best of both worlds so this is a very
promising Direction but it's still
probably a couple of years out but who
knows maybe we will see some of that I
think the base machinery for that is
there in the form of context functions
and contextual types but it might need
to be refined so that's
One Direction that we will observe and
however the community evolves we will
try to adopt tapir and the CTP to the
new libraries that come to light and as
I said it's not going to probably well
hopefully it's not going to be a very
hard job because we try to be flexible
in the approaches that we support
not we'll see probably there will be no
some work will need to be done so
another area that we are starting to
explore is can we also expose an
endpoint using grpc using the same
endpoint description as we are using for
the HTTP version so there's a preview
version of that and I think that's also
an interesting approach if you could
actually have a single description which
you know you can interpret as a grpc
endpoint as an HTTP endpoint although
there are some model differences in both
which make it hard so yeah we will just
have to you know experiment and see how
it evolves another direction is a
serverless which I think is also very
promising we can actually Leverage The
metadata that we have so we have the
whole metadata available to us at
runtime which we can actually use to
generate a serverless description of an
endpoint so there's already some code in
tapir which allows you to interpret at
up your endpoint as a Lambda function on
AWS right and it generates the whole
yaml for that for you so you just need
to you know there's one component that
generates the docker image which
actually runs the code and there's
another component which generates the
AWS configuration which you have to plug
in to actually expose the and configure
the Lambda so I think this that's also
an interesting direction of tapir maybe
there will be others as well into how
you can actually leverage the
description of an endpoint which I
haven't envisioned yet but these are our
most immediate plans also we would like
probably to stabilize the other modules
of tapir so so far we have stabilized
core and as far as 1 0 is out we are
there's a guarantee that you know things
will be binary compatible between
releases we should probably do the same
for the server and client modules so
it's not like the most exciting work or
the most visible work so you probably
won't see a lot of interesting features
out there but it's something that needs
to be done not just because it's nice
for the users to know that they won't
have to do any code changes between
tapiro releases so yeah I guess that's
our plans for the for the next half year
at least
I'm glad to hear about the yaml
generation for serverless I am also not
a fan of writing too much yaml so how
can listeners learn more about you and
software Mill and I will put the links
in the show notes I think the best way
is to visit our blog we try to put a lot
of emphasis on writing good technical
blogs on subjects that we find
interesting so we have a whole incentive
program in our company so that people
actually share what they learn by
writing blogs I think it's a very nice
skill to have to be able to communicate
efficiently in writing and it's also
what I practice I write quite a lot of
blogs so I think the technical blog is a
great place to start we do a lot of
content on functional programming on
event sourcing well and a lot of other
subjects as well I would also invite
people to try out the tap your
documentation we try to put a lot of
effort into writing actually good dogs
so that you can easily find solutions to
your problems there's a generator where
you can generate a simple tapier project
it's called adopt adapir so maybe you
can try it out and you just preview the
code so you can see if the way the code
looks seems nice to you and seems
elegant and hopefully we will make a
good first impression that's great
thanks for taking the time today Adam
thank you this is Philip Winston for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening